Guide to the Elaine Lobl Konigsburg Papers, 1967-1986 SC.1986.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Elaine Lobl Konigsburg Papers
1966-1991
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Konigsburg, Elaine Lobl
SC.1986.01
11.21 Linear Feet (12 manuscript boxes and 3 oversize boxes)
Elaine Lobl Konigsburg (February 10, 1930-April 19, 2013) was a writer and illustrator of children's books and young adult fiction and one of six writers to win two Newbery Medals. The collections contains material relating to her books published between 1967 and 1991, including: manuscripts, typescripts, galleys, some correspondence with publishers, dust jackets, original illustrations and art.
Biography
Elaine Lobl Konigsburg (February 10, 1930-April 19, 2013) was a writer and illustrator of children's books and young adult fiction. Born in New York City in 1930, she grew up in Pennsylvania and graduated as valedictorian of her Farrell, Pa., high school. Shortly after, she met her husband, David Konigsburg, at a meatpacking plant where she worked as a bookkeeper.
She received her undergraduate degree at the Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie Mellon University), where she majored in chemistry and continued her studies as a graduate student at the University of Pittsburgh. She soon realized that chemistry might not be the career path for her, as she is quoted as saying: "Long before I began writing, long before I had children, I was a chemist. Determined to push back the frontiers of science, I continued studying chemistry at the University of Pittsburgh graduate school. After two years there I found that the only thing I had succeeded in pushing back was my hairline, I twice blew up a laboratory sink, losing my eyebrows and banks in a flash."
She relocated to Jacksonville, Florida, after her husband was offered a job as an industrial psychologist. There, Elaine taught at the Bartram School for Girls until 1955, when she gave birth to her first child, Paul. Elaine would have two more children, Laurie and then Ross, in 1955 and 1959. While raising her children, she took painting lessons through a local adult education program.
After the family relocated again, this time to Port Chester, New York, and once all three children were in school, Elaine began to write. Her first published book was Jennifer, Hecate, Macbeth, William McKinley, and Me, Elizabeth in 1967, which was a Newbery Honor winner and selected by Book Week Magazine as an honor book for its 1967 Children's Spring Book Festival. This was followed, in the same year, by From, the Mixed-up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler, which was awarded a Newbery Medal. For both, she used her children as the models for illustrations. In the 1973 film version of the book, Ingrid Bergman played the role of Mrs. Frankweiler, which was also made into a television movie in 1995, with Lauren Bacall in the same role.
Konigsburg went on to publish over 20 books. In 1997, she won a second Newbery Medal for The View from Saturday, making her one of six writers to win two Newbery Medals.
"Many of Konigsburg's stories feature childhood and adolescent struggles that are easy for school-age readers to understand. Often her characters are striving to find the answers to big questions that will help shape their identities. Many of them are based on her own experiences as a child, the observations she made of children while a teacher, and the experiences or observations of her children."
Konigsburg passed away in Falls Church, Va., on April 19, 2013.
Separated Material
The collection originally contained the following foreign language first editions that were shelved with the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room general collection and are now located in storage, part of Special Collection's Nesbitt Collection, and can be requested for in-library use in the reading room:
First editions of Jennifer, Hecate, Macbeth, William McKinley, and Me, Elizabeth from Germany, Finland, and Norway
First editions of From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler from Germany, Japan, Netherlands, and Norway
First edition of Georgie from Germany
Samuel Todd's Book of Great Colors
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in the following 15 series by book title and according to publication date. The final series contains oversize materials:
Series I. Jennifer, Hecate, Macbeth, William McKinley, and Me, Elizabeth
Series II. From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler
Series III. About the B'nai Bagels
Series IV. Altogether, One at a Time
Series V. George
Series VI. A Proud Taste for Scarlet and Miniver
Series VII. The Dragon in the Ghetto Caper
Series VIII. The Second Mrs. Giaconda
Series IX. Father's Arcane Daughter
Series X. Throwing Shadows
Series XI. Journey to an 800 Number
Series XII. Up from Jericho Tel
Series XIII. Samuel Todd's Book of Great Colors
Series XIV. Samuel Todd's Book of Great Inventions
Series XV. Oversize materials
Series XVI. Correspondence to Amy Kellman
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elaine Lobl Konigsburg in 1986. Series XVI, Gift of Amy Kellman in 2020.
Custodial History
The collection was originally housed in the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room at the University of Pittsburgh's Information Science Library. After the library's closure in 2012, the collection was transferred to the University of Pittsburgh Special Collections.
Scope and Content Notes
The Elaine Lobl Konigsburg Papers include material relating to her books published between 1967 and 1991, including: manuscripts, typescripts, galleys, some correspondence with publishers, dust jackets, original illustrations and art.
Series are arranged in chronological order according to the date of publication. Folders within each series are arranged according to the order of the publication process. Both series and folders remain in the same arrangement as when received from the Information Sciences Library, excluding galley proofs and illustrations which are now located within oversized materials.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Elaine Lobl Konigsburg Papers, 1967-1986, SC.1986.01, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Women authors, American -- 20th century; Illustrators -- United States -- Juvenile literature; Children's stories, American; Children's books -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 20th century; Konigsburg, Elaine Lobl
- Jennifer, Hecate, Macbeth, William McKinley, and me, Elizabeth, 1967; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains materials related to Konigsburg's first published book, Jennifer, Hecate, Macbeth, William McKinley, and Me, Elizabeth., published in 1967. Although none of the material within the series is dated, based the book's publication date, materials were most likely created throughout the 1960's. The series is arranged according to the editing and publication process and includes handwritten manuscripts and typescripts, notes, proofs, and dust jackets. Galley proofs and illustrations are included in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Handwritten manuscript (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Typescript with author's revisions (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Typescript as submitted (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Typescript with notes to typesetter and corrections (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Handwritten notes with references to galley and book (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Illustrations with Jennifer's notes in script mounted on typeset leaves (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Folded and gathered proof and dust jacket (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dust jackets (Box 1, Folder 9)
- From the Mixed-up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler, 1967; II.
  Found in this series are materials related to Konigsburg's second book, From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler, published in 1967. Although a majority of the material within the series is not dated, based on the books publication date and what is dated, materials were most likely created throughout the mid 1960's. The series is arranged according to the editing and publications process and includes typescripts, proofs, correspondence, and proposed dust jackets. Galley proofs and illustrations are located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Typescript (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Folded and gathered proof and correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dust jackets (2), one with Newbery Medal (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Illustrated note cards and envelopes, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photo reproductions of museum floor plans (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Illustration (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 7)
- About the B'nai Bagels, 1969; III.
  Included in this series are materials related to Konigsburg's third book, About the B'nai Bagels, published in 1969. Although everything but the correspondence is undated, of the material within based on the books publication date, materials were most likely created throughout the mid to late 1960's. Included are handwritten manuscripts and typescripts, proofs, and correspondence. Oversize materials, like galley proofs and illustrations are included in Series XV.
  - Handwritten Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Typescript, 2nd Draft (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Typescript, Carbon and Photocopy (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Typescript with Jacket and Dedication Information (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Editor's Comments (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Folded and Gathered Proof (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from H. Goldstein from Atheneum, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Altogether, One at a Time, 1971; IV.
  This series includes materials related to the publication of Konigsburg's fourth book, Altogether, One at a Time, a short story collection published in 1971. Included are handwritten manuscripts and typescripts-many with revisions, notes, and correspondence. Although very little of the material within the series is dated, based on the books publication date those items that are dated, materials were most likely created throughout mid to late 1960's. There is one galley proof which is located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Typescript (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Folded and Gathered Proof (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dust jackets (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Handwritten Manuscript, "Inviting Jason" (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Typescript with Revisions, "Inviting Jason" (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Typescript, "Inviting Jason" (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Handwritten Notes, "Specific Dyslexia" and "The Last Skill Acquired" (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Robert M. Savage, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Typescript, "Night of the Leonids," including letter to Jean Karl, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Partial Manuscript, "The Night of the Leonids" (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Typescript, "The Night of the Leonids" (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Handwritten Notes, "Shower of the Leonids", 1966 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Handwritten Manuscript, "Camp Fat" (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Typescript, "Camp Fat," with corrections and revisions (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Partial Typescript, "Camp Fat" (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Black and White Photo Reproductions of Illustrations, "Camp Fat" (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Handwritten Manuscript, "Momma at the Pearly Gates" (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Typescript with Revisions, "Momma at the Pearly Gates" (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Typescript, "Momma at the Pearly Gates" (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Photo reproductions of illustrations (Box 3, Folder 25)
- George, 1971; V.
  This small series includes materials related to George, published in 1971. The title actually appears as (george). Two items are included in this small series, notes and sketches and a manuscript. Although none of the material within the series is dated, based on the books publication date, materials were most likely created throughout the late 1960's.
  - Notes and Sketches (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript (Box 4, Folder 2)
- A Proud Taste for Scarlet and Miniver, 1973; VI.
  Included in this series are materials related to Konigsburg's fictionalized account of Eleanor of Aquitaine, A Proud Taste for Scarlet and Miniver, publised in 1973. Handwritten manuscripts and typescripts, correspondence, proofs, and proposed dust jackets make up this series. Although the only dated materials within the series is correspondence, based on this and the book's publication date, materials were most likely created throughout the late 1960's and early 1970's.
  - Handwritten manuscript (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Typescript, partially handwritten (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Typescript with note, "Dear Colette" (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Typescript with revisions (Box 4, Folder 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence from Colette M. Coman, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence from Jean Karl, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Illustrations for dust jacket (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Dust jackets (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Folded and gathered proof (Box 4, Folder 6)
- The Dragon in the Ghetto Caper, 1974; VII.
  This series includes materials related to Konigsburg's 7th book, The Dragon in the Ghetto Caper, published in 1974. Although a majority of the material within the series is not dated, based on the books publication date, materials were most likely created throughout the early 1970's. Included are handwritten manuscripts and typescripts, proofs, and correspondence. Oversize materials, such as galley proofs and illustrations can be found in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Handwritten manuscript, some typed (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Typescript with revisions (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Typescript (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Galley proof, cut 4.4"x8" (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous proofs (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Folded and gathered proof (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Color selection chart, "Pantone 158" (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Color selection chart card with green swatches (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence from Harriet Barton, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Illustrations (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence to Matt Martino from Harriet Barton (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
- The Second Mrs. Gianconda, 1974-1987; VIII.
  Included in this series are items related to The Second Mrs. Gianconda, a historical novel featuring Leonardo da Vinci, published in 1975. Although very little of the material within this series is dated, based on the books publication date, materials were most likely created throughout the early 1970's. Included are handwritten manuscripts and typescripts, notes, correspondence, proofs, and the dramatization of the book make up this series. One galley proof and a dramatization of the book book, are located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Handwritten Manuscript (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Typescript with Revisions (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Handwritten Notes (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Typescript with revisions (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Jean Karl, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Typescript (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Proof, folded and gathered (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dust jacket (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dramatization of book-manuscript and notes, partly handwritten, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Dramatization of book, typescript (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Dramatization of book, typescript 2 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dramatization of book, typescript 3 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Dramatization of book-notes and revisions (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Film (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Audio tape (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, February 24, 1976-March 2, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Father's Arcane Daughter, IX.
  This series includes typescripts for Father's Arcane Daughter, published in 1976. It was later published as My Father's Daughter. Although none of the material within the series is dated, according the book's publication date, materials were most likely created throughout early to mid- 1970's. There is one galley proof located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Typescript with handwritten revisions (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Typescript, some pages handwritten and some pages missing (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Typescript (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Typescript with print notes (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Typescript with print notes (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Throwing Shadows, X.
  This series includes handwritten manuscripts, typescripts, and a gathered proof for Throwing Shadows, a short story collection published in 1979. Although none of the material within the series is dated, based on the books publication date, materials were most likely created throughout the mid 1970's. One galley proof is located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Handwritten Manuscript (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Typescript "The Catchee" (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Typescript with handwritten revisions "Assertiveness Training" (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Typescript, missing section under heading "On Shark's Tooth Beach" (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Typescript with artwork and notes (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Folded and gathered proof (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Journey to an 800 Number, XI.
  Included in this series are materials related to Journey to an 800 Number, published in 1982. Handwritten manuscripts, typescripts, and correspondence make up this series. Although the only dated materials are the correspondence, based on this and the publication date, materials were most likely created during the late 1970's and early 1980's. Oversize illustrations are located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Manuscript, mostly handwritten (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Typescript (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Typescript photocopies (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Typescript photocopies (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Revisions (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Robert Lescher and Jean Karl, March 31, 1981-November 16, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Typescript with print note (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Up From Jericho Tel, XII.
  This series includes typescripts, correspondence, and photographs for Konigsburg's only speculative fiction novel, Up From Jericho Tel, published in 1986. The only dated material in the series is the correspondence, but based on this and the book's publication date, materials were most likely created during the early to mid-1980's. One galley proof for the novel can be found in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Typescript (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence from Jean Karl, Jonathan J. Lanman, and Michele A. Foley, August 19, 1985-March 17,1986 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Drafts of Cover Art and Final Dust Jacket (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Samuel Todd's Book of Great Colors, 1988-1990; XIII.
  Included in this series are materials related to Konigsburg's picture book, Samuel Todd's Book of Great Colors, published in 1990. Originally created just for her grandson, Samuel Todd, her editor, decided it should be published. Materials included are the original handmade book, typescript, various proofs, correspondence, and rough cuts of the printed pages. One galley proof is located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Original handmade book (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Dummy book with note, November 10, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Typescript, January 18, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Color proof 1, June 7, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Color proof 2, July 25, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from editor Jean Karl, December 17, 1987-May 24, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Samuel Todd in Jon Lauman's office with note, October 27, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Printed pages, rough cut, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Samuel Todd's Book of Great Inventions, 1989-1991; IV.
  This series contains materials related to the children's picture book Samuel Todd's Book of Great Inventions, published in 1991, and includes typescripts, proofs, correspondence, and proposed dust jackets. Box 14 contains all of the illustrations for the book, located in Series XV, "Oversize Materials."
  - Dummy 1 and typescript, December 28, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Dummy 2-carried to NYC on 6/14/1990 and shown to J.K., J.L. and B.F., June 14, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Typescripts, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Color proof 1 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Galley proofs 1, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Color proof 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Color proof 3 with correspondence, April 11, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Galley proofs and memo from editor, September 10, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dust jackets and color swatches (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Samuel Todd with notes, April 15, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Illustration test shot (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from E.L. Konigsburg, January 18, 1990-October 10, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence to E.L. Konigsburg, September 22, 1989-April 11, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Proofs (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Promotional material-MacMillan catalog Fall 1991 and correspondence, June 10, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Oversize Materials, 1967-1990; V.
  This series contains galley proofs and illustrations and is divided between 3 boxes.
  - Galley Proofs, 1967-1990; 1.
    - Jennifer, Hecate, Macbeth, William McKinley, and Me, Elizabeth (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler, contains 2 galley proofs, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - About the B'nai Bagels (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
    - Altogether, One at a Time, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - A Proud Taste for Scarlet and Miniver, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - The Dragon In The Ghetto Caper, contains 2 galley proofs, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - The Dragon in the Ghetto Caper, reproduction and master reproduction (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - The Second Mrs. Giaconda, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Father's Arcane Daughter, contains 2 galley proofs, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Throwing Shadows, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Journey to an 800 Number (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Up from Jericho Tel (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Samuel Todd's Book of Great Colors, Galley #2, 1990 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Illustrations, 2.
    - From the Mixed-Up Files of Mrs. Basil E. Frankweiler
      - Two children in front of tomb, p.107 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Two children at ticket window, p.121 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - About the B'nai Bagel
      One of the illustrations, "Cookie, Mark, and bagel," due to its size, is located in box 14.
      - Baseball team, title page and back dust cover (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Mark with spoon to light, pg.7 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Mark, Dad, and soup pot, p.23 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Mark and Spencer with clipboard, p.43 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Mother, Mark, and Spencer at attention, p.81 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Cookie, Mark, and Bagel, pg. 104-105 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Mother signaling a bunt, p.145 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Mother, children, and Dad at table, p.161 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - The Dragon in the Ghetto Caper
      - Edie looking at dragon picture, pg.11 (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - "Gone elsewhere," p.19 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Andy and Edie in the car, p.25 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Three eggs in basket, p.59 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Child waving, p.95 (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Boy spraying man in the face, p.108 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Man at adding machine, p.117 (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Layovers and Drafts of Title Page (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Illustrations and Drafts of Illustrations (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Samuel Todd's Book of Great Inventions
      - Illustration for feet (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Illustration for standing (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Illustration of sleeping (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Illustration for candles (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Illustration for Velcro (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Illustration for belts (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Illustration for mirrors (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Illustration for wheels (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Illustration for gloves (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Illustration for backpacks (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Illustration for thermos (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Illustration for ladders (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Illustration for boxes (Box 14, Folder 14)